# **Curriculum Vitae**

# **Christopher James Shepherd**

6 Keats Apartments, Croydon, CRO 2FT



chris\_shepherd2@hotmail.com +447929 672636 www.chrisshepherd.io www.github.com/cshep4/

Full clean driving licence Car owner

#### **Profile**

Highly motivated and skilled software development professional with three years' experience in software design, development and integration. Proficient in several programming languages such as Java, Kotlin, PHP, C++, JavaScript, Go and SQL with knowledge in various agile software development methodologies.

#### Experience

## October 2015-Present – IBM, Developer:

- Currently working as a back-end developer using Java 8 and Spring Boot with Maven. We use Jenkins for Continuous Integration and SonarQube for code quality analysis. GitLab is used as source control. Our application uses RabbitMQ as a JMS message broker and Redis for cache management.
- I am using various software development techniques such as Test Driven Development and Agile SAFE.
- Prior to my current role, I was a full stack developer writing in Java, using Spring Boot with Gradle and AngularJS to create a mobile app. The project used TDD and pair programming. Jenkins was also used for Continuous Integration and GitHub for version control.
- I also worked on a project taking the role of a Java developer for a large external client in the insurance industry. This was using the Spring MVC framework. This was carried out using the Scrum framework.
- Responsibilities for each project have included developing user stories, fixing defects and code reviewing.
- Carried out a short cognitive side project for a PoC. I created a back-end using Node.js and Express to link a mobile app with IBM's Watson Conversation web service and a Cloudant NoSQL database.
- I have undertaken several training courses, both technical and non-technical, including MEAN Stack, Core Java, Java Spring and an Agile DevOps Workshop.
- I am part of the Blockchain Practice Area, this involves carrying out training and gaining the IBM Blockchain Essentials for Developers certification.
- I have taken and passed the Oracle Certified Java Associate certification and plan to take the next level, Oracle Certified Java Programmer certification within the next quarter.

#### May 2012-September 2012; June 2013-August 2014 – Motor Design Ltd, Software Developer:

Motor Design Ltd is a company that produces Motor-CAD, a thermal analysis software package for electric motors and generators. I carried out an industrial placement year as part of my degree and was subsequently nominated by them for the Placement Student of the Year award.

- Learned and utilised advanced skills programming in Object Pascal using Delphi XE2, creating various features for a software package by interpreting physics and mathematical equations.
- Created conductor placement and magnetic winding design tools for Motor-CAD.
- Produced an interactive editor for solver circuit design also for Motor-CAD.
- Implemented functionality for Motor-CAD to check for updates using a PHP script I created on the company
  website.
- Greatly developed my analytical skills and programming ability, as well as encouraging working using my own initiative.

#### Education

## <u>De Montfort University, Leicester – First Class BSc Hons, Computer Games Programming:</u>

2014-2015 – Third year modules: Games Programming

Mobile Games Development

Secure Web Application Development

Fuzzy Logic and Knowledge Based Systems (AI) Final Year Project (Social media web application)

2012-2013 – Second year modules: C++ for Games Programmers

Artificial Intelligence and Modelling for Games

Introduction to Graphics and Interactive 3D Modelling

Database Design and Implementation

2011-2012 – First year modules: C++ Programming

Games Architecture, Design and Development

**Creative Client Computing** 

**Computer Systems** 

## Shrewsbury Sixth Form College, Shrewsbury:

2009-2011 – A-Levels: Computing, Mathematics, Physics

## Lakelands School, Sports and Languages College:

2004-2009 – GCSEs: 9 GCSEs grade A-C, including Mathematics, English and Science.

## **Relevant Projects**

1. Created various applications whilst at University using C++ including a 3D game engine from scratch.

- 2. A gym tracking application where users can log in, store their performance in the gym and view progress with various analytics. Written in HTML/CSS, PHP, MySQL and JavaScript with some APIs rewritten in Kotlin using Spring Boot. This is written with an MVC architecture. The website is hosted using Heroku and the MySQL database is hosted using AWS Relational Database Service. The website URL is <a href="https://www.gyme.co.uk">www.gyme.co.uk</a>.
- 3. Redeveloped the mobile game I originally created at University, "Monster Attack" from scratch. This is now written using Java 8 and is fully unit tested. I plan to release this to the Google Play Store in the near future.
- 4. A World Cup 2018 Predictor app in the Ionic Framework, with back-end APIs written in Kotlin using Spring Boot. The intention of the app is for users to compete against friends by predicting football scores for the 2018 World Cup. Up to date fixtures and results are fetched from an external API. The back-end of the app was written entirely using TDD and is hosted on Heroku. The app uses adverts to generate revenue provided by Google's Admob service. The app was released to the Apple App Store and Google Play Store. I decided to take this app down from the app stores once the World Cup finished though, with a final user count of 6812.
- 5. A Premier League Predictor app extended from the World Cup Predictor. This is also used to compete against friends by predicting scores for the 18/19 Premier League. This app contains a lot of new features, such as live match scores and commentary. The back-end uses Spring Boot scheduler to update the matches from an external API and uses websockets to send the data to the mobile device. The back-end is also written entirely using TDD and hosted on Heroku. This is currently available on the Apple App Store and Google Play Store. The app uses adverts to generate revenue provided by Google's Admob service.
- 6. A portfolio website built in Angular 6, with a small serverless back-end written in Go. The front-end is hosted on Firebase and the back-end on AWS Lambda. This can be found at <a href="www.chrisshepherd.io">www.chrisshepherd.io</a>, along with more details about my other projects.

## **Interests and Hobbies**

My first passion is sport, particularly football and hockey. I support Liverpool Football Club and attend most of their home matches. I have played hockey for Oswestry Hockey Club, school, college and university. I was chosen to be captain for my secondary school, which helped develop my ability to work in a team and leadership skills. I follow the sport of Rugby League and I support the charity Rugby League Cares, which aims to help families or people who have been affected by rugby injuries.